<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<elements>
	<info>
		<name>Zailm</name>
		<update version="0.0.1">
			<file name="race-Zailm.xml" url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/GEIIOW/Faleria/refs/heads/master/user-gellow/race-zailm.xml" />
		</update>
	</info>
	<element name="Zailm" type="Race" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACE_ZAILM">
		<description>
			<p class="flavor">“My work may not yet be complete, but these creatures show just how grandiose my purpose is. After years of work, I’ve finally made substancial progress when it comes to using the power of souls. The men and women that were part of my latest test, of trying to power a dead body with only the power of a soul, have been reanimated as something more than they were before. While they still don’t seem to have memories of their previous life, they have become stronger, some have become faster and more resilient. Nothing less than a complete success.”</p>
				<p class="indent">- Y. Mageshell, Manyhals of Death</p>
				<p class="indent">The Zailm are reborn warriors who can’t get a grasp of their past. Originating from Zeiloryn, these once mortal humanoids scattered throughout Faleria in seach of themselves. While their past may be lost to them, their future is full of potencial due to their mind being null of previous abilities and their new enhanced physiology.</p>
			
			 <h4>IMORTALIZED MORTALS</h4>
				<p>Zailm don’t all hail from a shared mortal type. There are those who seem to have been human, others who are of a smaller stature and resemble halflings or gnomes and even those who tower over the tallest of mortals. Their state of decay is irrelevant to their functionallity, so it’s possible to see some Zailm who are missing limbs, jaws or much more of their bodies, while others are in pristine condition, only being recognised as Zailm due to their shared grayish skin tone.</p>
				<p class="indent">Despite this military power, it is far more common for Vlandaer to be on the defensive rather than on the attack as they only sought refuge from a world that didn’t accept them. Something that may be bound to change.</p>

			 <h4>THE VALLEY OF DEATH</h4>
				<p>Many of those who get reanimated as Zailm completely lose their mind, turning into yet another angry and feral undead creature, while the ones who manage to retain their sanity tend to present a high degree of functionality and capacity for civility. Though often times prosecuted without just cause, many zailm are sought as hired swords when times get tough.</p>
				<p class="indent">Ostracized from certain parts of the world, some of these reborn abominations chose to gather and make a kingdom of their own in Manyhal where they now reside. Since creating their kingdom of Vlandaer, the zailm have found a way to recreate their creators formula to create more of their own kind, giving them an ever growing army.</p>
				<p class="indent">Despite this military power, it is far more common for Vlandaer to be on the defensive rather than on the attack as they only sought refuge from a world that didn’t accept them. Something that may be bound to change.</p>

			 <h4>A SHAPELESS KIND</h4>
				<p>Zailm is more of a title than a descriptor of a person. When we talk about a human we know they have, usually, 4 appendages, a head and a torso, not the zailm though. These beings have been stitched together piece by piece, making some unrecognizable. All zailm have grayish skin or fur but not all have both of their arms and legs. Some don’t have their lower jaw, some have horns on their head, some have them somewhere else. Some look as if they aren’t deceased at all, others make you wonder how they’re moving at all. How the population treats zailm depends on how grotesque they appear to be.</p>		

			 <h4>ZAILM NAMES</h4>
				<p>It is to expect that a type of people robbed of their past and thrown into the world would name themselves whatever came to mind, but that’s not the case. For the zailm that are part of Vlandaer, the names they have adopted are a tribute to the great empire’s capital city that once stood just north of their own border, so they choose names that we would call greco-romanic. For those outside of that kingdom they can either choose their own name based on the culture they inhabit or, on very rare cases, remember their name from when they were alive.</p>		


			<h4>ZAILM TRAITS</h4>
			<p>Zailm seem to have been reborn with an assortment of new abilities.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong>You may choose to increase an ability score by 2 and one other ability score by one or increase three different ability scores by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Age.</em></strong>It is unkown for how long the source of you new life can support it. Zailm don’t age, but will resume rotting when they reach 0 hit points or if their connection to their source of new life is broken.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Creature Type.</em></strong>You are an Undead.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Size.</em></strong>The size of Zailm is dependent on their previous life and there doesn’t seem to exist a medium of height nor weight. Your size is either Small or Medium.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Speed.</em></strong>Your base walking speed is 30 feet.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Sunlight Sensitivity.</em></strong>The decomposition that affected your sight has made you sensitive to intense sunlight. You have disadvantage on attack rolls and on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight when you, the target of your attack, or whatever you are trying to perceive is in direct sunlight.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ethereal Sight.</em></strong>You can see 60 feet into the Ethereal Plane when you are on the Material Plane and vice versa.</p>
		</description>
		
		<sheet display="false" />
    	<setters> <!-- sera necessário ? -->
      		<set name="names" type="male">Ander, Blath, Bran, Frath, Geth, Lander, Luth, Malcer, Stor, Taman, Urth</set>
      		<set name="names" type="female">Amafrey, Betha, Cefrey, Kethra, Mara, Olga, Silifrey, Westra</set>
      		<set name="names" type="surname">Brightwood, Helder, Hornraven, Lackman, Stormwind, Windrivver</set>
      		<set name="names-format">{{name}} {{surname}}</set>
      		<set name="height" modifier="2d10">4'8"</set>
      		<set name="weight" modifier="2d4">110 lb.</set>
    	</setters>
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed" value="30" bonus="base"/>
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Ability Score Increase by 2 (ZAILM)" supports="Zailm" optional="true"/>
			<select type="Racial Trait" name="Ability Score Increase by 1 (ZAILM)" supports="Zailm" optional="true"/>
			<grant type="Size" id="ID_SIZE_MEDIUM" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GALITARKO_CLAWS" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	
		<!-- ability score by 2-->
		
		<element name="Ability Score Increase (Strength)" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ZAILM_STRENGTH">
			<compendium display="false" />
			<supports>Zailm</supports>
			<description>
				<p>Your Strength score increases by 2.</p>
			</description>
			<rules>
				<stat name="strength" value="2"/>
			</rules>
		</element>
	
		<element name="Ability Score Increase (Dexterity)" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ZAILM_DEXTERITY">
			<compendium display="false" />
			<supports>Zailm</supports>
			<description>
				<p>Your Dexterity score increases by 2.</p>
			</description>
			<rules>
				<stat name="dexterity" value="2"/>
			</rules>
		</element>
	

		<!-- traites-->
		
	<element name="Claws" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GALITARKO_CLAWS">
		<description>
			<p>Your claws are natural melee weapons, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with them, you deal slashing damage equal to 1d6 + your Strength modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Your claws are natural melee weapons, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with them, you deal slashing damage equal to 1d6+{{strength:modifier}}, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>  
	
	<element name="Mauling Strike" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GALITARKO_MAULING_STRIKE">
		<description>
			<p>Immediately after you move at least 20 feet, you can make one melee attack with your claws as a bonus action.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>Immediately after you move at least 20 feet, you can make one melee attack with your claws as a bonus action.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>

	<element name="Bearable" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GALITARKO_BEARABLE">
		<description>
			<p>You count as one size larger when determining your carrying capacity and the weight you can push, drag, or lift.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet>
			<description>You count as one size larger when determining your carrying capacity and the weight you can push, drag, or lift.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	
	<element name="Galitarko Mortal Subtype" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_GALITARKO_SUBTYPE">
		<description>
			<p>Three main subtypes of galitarko populate Faleria: Grizzly, Panda and Polar Galitarko. Choose one of these subtypes.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Sub Race" name="Galitarko subtype" supports="Galitarko" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	
	
	<!--subtypes-->
	<!--Grizzly-->
	<element name="Grizzly Galitarko" type="Sub Race" source="Faleria" id="ID_SUB_RACE_GALITARKO_GRIZZLY">
		<supports>Galitarko</supports>
		<description>
			<p> The grizzly galitarko wear a resemblance to either black, brown or grey bears. Natural of Manyhal and western Zeiloryn, these huge mortals can produce a fierce roar, 
			unlike any other. Though they might seem brutish, many carry the philosophy of Lendo, 
			that teaches you to always try to work for the greater good. In the case of the galitarko on the western side of Zeiloryn, 
			that meant joining the empire and it’s conquest. Grizzly galitarko often have only one name derived from an adjective given while they were young, such as Fasten, Hungrial, Madden and Swiffy.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Wisdom score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>High Climber.</em></strong> You have a climbing speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Keen Smell.</em></strong> You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Bearware.</em></strong> It takes an additional creature for you to be flanked or affected by pack tactics, or similar features.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read and write three languages of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="wisdom" value="1" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_HIGH_CLIMBER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_KEEN_SMELL" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BEARWARE" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LANGUAGES" />
		</rules>
	</element> 	
	<element name="High Climber" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_HIGH_CLIMBER">
		<description>
			<p>You have a climbing speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have a climbing speed equal to your walking speed.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed:climb" value="speed" bonus="base" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Keen Smell" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_KEEN_SMELL">
		<description>
			<p>You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Bearware" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BEARWARE">
		<description>
			<p>It takes an additional creature for you to be flanked or affected by pack tactics, or similar features.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>It takes an additional creature for you to be flanked or affected by pack tactics, or similar features.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Languages" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LANGUAGES">
		<description>
			<p>You can speak, read and write three languages of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Grizzly)" supports="Common" />
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Grizzly)" supports="Common" />
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Grizzly)" supports="Common" />
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Panda-->
	<element name="Panda Galitarko" type="Sub Race" source="Faleria" id="ID_SUB_RACE_GALITARKO_PANDA">
		<supports>Galitarko</supports>
		<description>
			<p>The panda galitarko wear a resemblance to either giant, qinling or red pandas. Natural of Issadrem, these spot furred mortals are known for their selflessness. Followers of the Iendu philosophy, that teaches you to follow the path to self improvement and communal harmony. They protect their lands and those of others even if that means taking up arms.Panda galitarko follow the naming convention that’s prevalent in Issadrem, with two different parts separated by an apostrophe. The first part functions as a one syllable family name and the second as a name for each person. Examples of this naming convention are ones such as Sur’Tzen, Gar’Meren, Pol’Jalgoren and Gra’Cious.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Charisma score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>High Climber.</em></strong> You have a climbing speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Bearfriend.</em></strong> You have advantage on Charisma (Persuasion) checks.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Roll-up.</em></strong> If you are not wearing heavy armor, when enemies try to shove you into the prone condition you are pushed 5 feet away instead. Additionaly, standing up from prone only takes 5 feet of movement, if you are not wearing heavy armor.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read and write three languages of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="wisdom" value="1" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_HIGH_CLIMBER" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BEARFRIEND" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ROLLUP" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LANGUAGES2" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_IXALI" />
		</rules>
	</element> 	
	<element name="High Climber" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_HIGH_CLIMBER">
		<description>
			<p>You have a climbing speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have a climbing speed equal to your walking speed.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed:climb" value="speed" bonus="base" />
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Bearfriend" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BEARFRIEND">
		<description>
			<p>You have advantage on Charisma (Persuasion) checks.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have advantage on Charisma (Persuasion) checks.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Roll-up" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_ROLLUP">
		<description>
			<p>If you are not wearing heavy armor, when enemies try to shove you into the prone condition you are pushed 5 feet away instead. Additionaly, standing up from prone only takes 5 feet of movement, if you are not wearing heavy armor.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>If you are not wearing heavy armor, when enemies try to shove you into the prone condition you are pushed 5 feet away instead. Additionaly, standing up from prone only takes 5 feet of movement, if you are not wearing heavy armor.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Languages" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_LANGUAGES2" >
		<description>
			<p>You can speak, read and write Ixali and one other language of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Panda Galitarko)" supports="Common" restrict="-Ixali"/>
		</rules>
	</element>

	<!--Polar-->
	<element name="Polar Galitarko" type="Sub Race" source="Faleria" id="ID_SUB_RACE_GALITARKO_POLAR">
		<supports>Galitarko</supports>
		<description>
			<p>The polar galitarko wear a resemblance to polar bears. Natural to Nyjörsa, these mortals are followers of the Stengul philosophy, that teaches you to first take care of yourself and your closest allies and only then think of others. Due to this, these galitarko tend to stay in small packs or even all alone and have nomadic tendencies. Polar galitarko names have a lot of vowels, particularly ones that necessitate the rounding of the lips such as Oulow, Gaupo, Urrobon and Abapaoa.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Ability Score Increase.</em></strong> Your Constituion score increases by 1.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Freezing Waters.</em></strong> You have a swim speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Keen Sight.</em></strong> You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Bearly Ready.</em></strong> When you roll initiative you can grant advantage to an ally within 30 ft. while granting disadvantage on yourself.</p>
			<p class="indent"><strong><em>Languages.</em></strong> You can speak, read and write Smidian and one other language of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<stat name="constitution" value="1" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FREEZING_WATERS" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_KEEN_SIGHT" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BEARLY_READY" />
			<grant type="Racial Trait" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_POLAR_LANGUAGES" />
			<grant type="Language" id="ID_LANGUAGE_SMIDIAN" />
		</rules>
	</element> 	
	<element name="Freezing Waters" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_FREEZING_WATERS" >
		<description>
			<p>You have a swim speed equal to your walking speed.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have a swim speed equal to your walking speed.</description>
		</sheet>
		<rules>
			<stat name="innate speed:swim" value="speed" bonus="base"/>
		</rules>
	</element>
	<element name="Bearfriend" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_KEEN_SIGHT">
		<description>
			<p>You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Roll-up" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_BEARLY_READY">
		<description>
			<p>When you roll initiative you can grant advantage to an ally within 30 ft. while granting disadvantage on yourself.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false">
			<description>When you roll initiative you can grant advantage to an ally within 30 ft. while granting disadvantage on yourself.</description>
		</sheet>
	</element>
	<element name="Languages" type="Racial Trait" source="Faleria" id="ID_RACIAL_TRAIT_POLAR_LANGUAGES" >
		<description>
			<p>You can speak, read and write Smidian and one other language of your choice.</p>
		</description>
		<sheet display="false" />
		<rules>
			<select type="Language" name="Language (Polar Galitarko)" supports="Common" restrict="-Smidian"/>
		</rules>
	</element>



</elements>
